<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>Joao Dear</title>
	<link>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/</link>
	<description>Recent content in Blog Index on Joao Dear</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://joaodear.xyz/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>The Attitude</title>
		<link>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/attitude/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/attitude/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a jetty near where I live that people like to jump and dive off of.
One morning, I  was on the jetty and overheard a conversation between a man
nicknamed &lt;em&gt;Bigode&lt;/em&gt; (Portuguese for moustache), and another man. Bigode was
telling him about when the jetty used to have two long planks at it&amp;rsquo;s end that
allowed people to jump and dive easily, landing in a sandy patch amid the rocks
below the jetty. Back then, Bigode told the man, many more people came to the
jetty, and, naturally, among these people were some idiots. Occasionally, one
of these idiots would jump off without knowing how to swim, how to dive, or
maybe while drunk, and have an accident. Eventually these accidents motivated
the local government to have someone saw off the planks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this attempt at stopping idiots from having accidents however, Bigode
says he still see&amp;rsquo;s these accidents happen, and suggests that instead, the
local government should station two guards at the jetty to watch for idiots.
With all due respect to Bigode, this is a stupid idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes it stupid isn&amp;rsquo;t having someone guard the jetty and take care of
those who dive from it, that&amp;rsquo;s actually a much better idea than sawing off the
planks. What makes it stupid is the notion that such a function needs to be
delegated to a pair of specialized professionals and be made &lt;em&gt;official&lt;/em&gt; through
public policy. Heaven forbid that we (I and the afore mentioned characters, of
which there is at least one present on the jetty at &lt;strong&gt;literally every hour in
the day&lt;/strong&gt;) take it upon ourselves to look after newcomers. No no no, &lt;em&gt;ordinary
people&lt;/em&gt; cannot be trusted to do such a thing, these matters need to be handled
properly by &lt;em&gt;”experts“&lt;/em&gt; appointed by the shining members of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://geohot.github.io/blog/jekyll/update/2021/09/28/class-warfare.html&#34;&gt;”Professional Managerial Class“&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This attitude is quite pervasive nowadays, especially where I live. It&amp;rsquo;s the
attitude of those who haven&amp;rsquo;t ever created anything by themselves, &lt;em&gt;for
themselves&lt;/em&gt;. Those who are passengers in their own lives. Those who grew up
inside carefully structured environments that handed them goals and motivation
on a silver platter, and were taught that the right thing was to stay within
the structure, and that everyone outside is either a dreg or just plain
unsuccessful—that without that structure things &lt;em&gt;just don&amp;rsquo;t work&lt;/em&gt;,
because people can&amp;rsquo;t be trusted to govern themselves. Thus, due to their
upbringing, they&amp;rsquo;re unable to fathom that people &lt;em&gt;can in fact&lt;/em&gt; be self-driven
and would be able to thrive outside such an environment. Any suggestion of such
a possibility is dismissed as being naive. The funny thing is that, in their
case, they&amp;rsquo;re actually right. People like this &lt;em&gt;are in fact&lt;/em&gt; incapable of
self-government, due to how they&amp;rsquo;ve been molly-coddled their whole lives. And
it&amp;rsquo;s not even that these people are lazy in some way, many are actually quite
hard working, but they don&amp;rsquo;t do anything unless told or forced to do so
externally. After work they go home to &lt;em&gt;Netflix and Chill&lt;/em&gt;, simp for Twitch
streamers, go to the bar and have a beer, or engage in some other passively
consuming activity. They toil only for the purposes of others, never their own.
And if there&amp;rsquo;s no direct or immediate reward in something you can forget about
them doing it, even if it would benefit them indirectly or in the future.
Their &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_preference&#34;&gt;Time Preference&lt;/a&gt; is much
too high for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just any structure can bring this out in people. Only those that
systematically punish production and innovation, and reward non-production and
stagnation, that continually deprive individuals of their responsibility for
the upkeep of society and the pursuit of adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good rule of thumb for escaping this mindset: whenever you think
”Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be nice if &lt;em&gt;blah blah blah&lt;/em&gt; existed“ or ”Things
would be so much better if someone did &lt;em&gt;such and such&lt;/em&gt;“, don&amp;rsquo;t wait for
anyone—&lt;strong&gt;go and do it&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, for a red pill on the decivilising effects of these structures and idea
of Natural Order, read the first two chapters of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/HoppeDemocracyTheGodThatFailed&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Democracy: The God That Failed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Multi-line Regular Expressions - Is $ really an assertion?</title>
		<link>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/multi_line_regex/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/multi_line_regex/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve programmed for any amount of time you probably know about
regular expressions, the terse, sometimes unreadable, powerful syntax
for describing arbitrary patterns of text. They can match any sort of
pattern, be it a URL, an email address or a C function declaration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, despite their arbitrary matching power, most implementations and most
programs that use them are implicitly limited to doing single line matches.
You&amp;rsquo;ll become acutely aware of this if you try to use UNIX core utilities to do
any kind of simple parsing (preprocessing HTML or Markdown for example). Very
quickly you&amp;rsquo;ll turn to awk, annoyed at the fact that sed or grep are unable to
accomplish such a simple task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I discovered Rob Pike&amp;rsquo;s article
&lt;a href=&#34;http://doc.cat-v.org/bell_labs/structural_regexps/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;structural regular expressions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
which tackles this very problem, and was quite intrigued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution he provides is beautifully simple. Instead of tools like grep,
sed, awk, diff etc. reading a file one line at a time, make them read one
&lt;em&gt;byte&lt;/em&gt; at a time. This way, the implicit structure normally imposed on files
and streams by these tools disappears, and the user can provide their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by Pike&amp;rsquo;s article, I have decided to take a crack at redesigning some
core utilities with the afore mentioned limitations removed. And despite having
just started this project, I&amp;rsquo;ve found what I&amp;rsquo;ll argue is another curious
instance of implicit structure in the implementation of regular expressions:
the end-of-line assertion or &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a regular expression match function (or at least the ones I&amp;rsquo;ve looked at)
&lt;strong&gt;^&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; cause a skip to the next element of the expression without
consuming a character in the input, whenever what they assert is true. This
behaviour is semantically correct, &lt;strong&gt;^&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; just ask the question
”Am I at the beginning of a line?“ or ”Am I at the end of a
line?“. So, given this behaviour, when looking at the string ”foo
bar“ the expression ”^[a-z ]+$“ would return a match. But
what about the expression ”stupid\.$Kelly“ and the string
”Keep it simple, stupid.\nKelly Johnson“? Surprisingly, it won&amp;rsquo;t
match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem isn&amp;rsquo;t the newline character because the string ”foo bar\n“
would be matched by the first expression just fine. So why the heck won&amp;rsquo;t it work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s step through the execution of expression 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skip to the beginning of ”stupid.“ and match
&lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;u&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;p&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;d&lt;/strong&gt; and a literal dot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re at &lt;strong&gt;\n&lt;/strong&gt; in the string and &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; in the expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end-of-line assertion succeeds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We move to the next element in the expression &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the problem? The assertion only moves you along in the expression,
&lt;em&gt;not in the string&lt;/em&gt;. So, after the &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; assert succeeds we try and match
&lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt;, but we&amp;rsquo;re still at the newline character in the string. How do we fix
this you ask? It&amp;rsquo;s simple, make &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; consume a character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”But João“ you exclaim, ”it&amp;rsquo;s semantically incorrect for an
assertion to consume a character!“&lt;br&gt;
To this I say: &lt;em&gt;Is &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; really an assertion?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I would argue that it &lt;em&gt;isn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt;, or rather that it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be treated the same
as &lt;strong&gt;^&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asserting a beginning-of-line, you need to check that either you&amp;rsquo;re at the
beginning of the string, or that the last character you looked at was a newline.
Notice that this has &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; to do with the current character in the string, so
it would be wrong to walk along to the next character.
On the other hand, when asserting an end-of-line, you need to check that either
you&amp;rsquo;re at the end of the string, or that the character you&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;currently&lt;/em&gt;
looking at is a null terminator or a newline. In the case of &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt;, it &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt;
matter what the current character in the string is, so why should it not behave
as though it matches something?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using standard behaviour, a &lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; assert becomes completely useless unless you
only put it at the end of the expression. So trying to check for an empty line
somewhere in the middle of the expression, for example, has to be done with
”^\n“, instead of ”^$“. Using our new behaviour, the
&lt;strong&gt;$&lt;/strong&gt; actually becomes useful in multi-line regular expressions and makes them
much more convenient to type, more syntactically consistent and more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>You Aren&#39;t What You Do!</title>
		<link>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/you_arent_what_you_do/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/you_arent_what_you_do/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I was chatting with a friend about this the other day, and it gave me the idea
for this post. It&amp;rsquo;s sort of a personal letter to myself, but it may be of use
to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What people do is one of the most common traits with which they identify.
Identification with a profession is taught to children very early on through
the age old question “What do you want to be when you grow up?”.
As kids grow into somewhat-jaded-angsty-teens, the toils of school or an
unfulfilling job are likely to cause identification with activities and
passions, external to their ordinary routine, such as music, drawing,
skateboarding, video games, studying obscure political theories etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is usually seen as harmless (especially compared to other things people
might identify with). However, I would argue the opposite, here are some
reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragility-of-self&#34;&gt;Fragility of Self&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your job defines you, what happens when you&amp;rsquo;re laid off, or your company
goes bankrupt? What about if you identify with playing the piano, and suddenly
develop arthritis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But João” you exclaim “[&lt;em&gt;insert random activity&lt;/em&gt;] is my
life, that couldn&amp;rsquo;t possibly happen to me!”. This made up answer is
obviously ridiculous, but it was chosen to show that a person who has tied
their identity to their occupation becomes intentionally blind to the
possibility of losing the ability to do it, because finding something else
would completely uproot their life—which will actually happen if they
lose said ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-isolation&#34;&gt;Social Isolation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you do basically nothing else outside your little niche, it becomes very
difficult to have a conversation someone. Quite frankly, the average person
doesn&amp;rsquo;t really care about the memory allocator you&amp;rsquo;re writing, or the
intricacies of Austrian Economic theory you&amp;rsquo;ve spent countless hours studying.
You may tell yourself that normal people are just boring or stupid, but that
kind of attitude just leaves you incredibly lonely, or with a social circle
with whom your only connection is this one super specific thing—probably
both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;snobbery&#34;&gt;Snobbery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, this kind of identification is likely to turn you into an arrogant,
sneering individual, particularly towards others in your domain. This happens
because viewing yourself in terms of your skill at a particular activity makes
any indication of &lt;em&gt;lack of skill&lt;/em&gt; extremely threatening. Such indication may
come from seeing others more skilled than you, but also from equally skilled
people that highlight the fact that you&amp;rsquo;re not as good as you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will cause you to be resentful, look down upon people to feel better,
dismiss peers because their success damages your self image and just be an
overall stuck up snob.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;just-take-it-easy&#34;&gt;Just Take it Easy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t do things you deeply enjoy and really
dedicate yourself to doing them well, just don&amp;rsquo;t make the mistake of believing
those things are somehow &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;. “&lt;em&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re so much more than that&lt;/em&gt;”
sounds kinda cringe but it&amp;rsquo;s true. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t let yourself become
pigeon-holed into one facet of life, make the effort to venture outside your
comfort zone and pursue different things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember: &lt;em&gt;stuff you do&lt;/em&gt; is just that, &lt;em&gt;stuff you do&lt;/em&gt;, and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Hello World!</title>
		<link>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/hello_world/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://joaodear.xyz/blog/hello_world/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ldquo_hello-there_rdquo&#34;&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Hello there!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was originally going to publish something much more &lt;em&gt;big braned&lt;/em&gt;
as this blog&amp;rsquo;s inaugural article. But, in wanting to publish before the year&amp;rsquo;s
end (and now having little time to do so), I&amp;rsquo;ve settled on writing a bit about
myself and some things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned in the past 2 years, which should serve as
a good pseudo-introduction to me and this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-collapse&#34;&gt;The Collapse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most people my age, I was expecting to enter &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; (air quotes) &lt;em&gt;new chapter
of life&lt;/em&gt; in 2020—also like most people, I ended up just being stuck
inside. For a good while at the beginning of the year I didn&amp;rsquo;t think much of
it. I was still doing a bit of university work, watching YouTube video&amp;rsquo;s was
still fun, and every now and then I&amp;rsquo;d go ride my bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point though, riding around your neighbourhood, doing homework and
&lt;em&gt;consooming&lt;/em&gt; a daily dose of Pewdiepie gets old. In fact, it gets old pretty
quick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;boredom&#34;&gt;Boredom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah yes&amp;hellip;good old boredom, a feeling I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had for quite a while (what with
the last year of school and all). I probably got bored sooner than
most of my friends because, at the time, I was afflicted by an odd tingling
pain in my arms whenever I tried to use them for anything either physically
intensive, or that demanded lot&amp;rsquo;s of repetitive motion on the part of my hands.
This meant: no guitar, no chatting on WhatsApp and most of all&amp;hellip;no video
games. So no, to this day I have not played Among Us, ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it was precisely at this time that things started to get interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some day in mid-April (maybe), I was so bored of scrolling through YouTube that
I decided I&amp;rsquo;d put my time to good use and learn something, and in trying to
think of something to learn I remembered that my Dad had told me once
“Hey you should learn Python! I bet you&amp;rsquo;d really like it”.
So I thought I&amp;rsquo;d give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual with these things, my Dad was right, and I eventually became (and
currently still am) totally obsessed with programming (shortly after he also
gave me the idea of trying Linux).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;nonsense&#34;&gt;Nonsense&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funny thing with Linux, VIM, programming languages and everything I
began encountering, is that &lt;strong&gt;none of it made any sense&lt;/strong&gt; (at first).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty commonsensical, new things usually don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt; make sense.
But the weird thing I noticed, and only just recently, is: &lt;em&gt;there is no
clear, rational process leading up to the understanding of new information&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across this idea reading Paul Feyerabend&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Against Method&lt;/em&gt; (whom I&amp;rsquo;ll probably
write about in future), and bar a few edge cases, I think it describes my
experience pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feyerabend&amp;rsquo;s argument is roughly that learning a new skill, conceptual
framework or language, doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen by carefully following the steps which
explain &lt;em&gt;clearly&lt;/em&gt; what is to be learned (except in the mind of a pedagogue or in
(((school))))—new information, if it is to be truly absorbed, cannot be offered
up to someone in pieces for them to logically assemble in to what appears to be
&lt;strong&gt;knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;. Instead, through playing, experimenting with and exposing
oneself to something new, there is a steady accumulation of what amounts
to &lt;strong&gt;nonsense&lt;/strong&gt;, but, if given enough time, this nonsense becomes so
rich that it suddenly crystallizes—like flipping a switch, what was once
unintelligible can now be understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this year everything I&amp;rsquo;ve learned, &lt;strong&gt;all of it&lt;/strong&gt;, was learned by
persisting through nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-years-end&#34;&gt;At Year&amp;rsquo;s End&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the spirit of the new year, I leave you with 2 little rules of thumb:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You break out of old (sometimes bad) habits when you&amp;rsquo;re bored.&lt;br&gt;
Boredom is your friend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t stop when none of what you&amp;rsquo;re learning makes sense (especially if the resources
you have on the subject are terrible, that&amp;rsquo;s where you&amp;rsquo;ll discover something new).&lt;br&gt;
Become comfortable with nonsense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bid you all a (late) Merry Christmas, and a Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
